Let's continue our discovery of caches and cover advanced cache design and cache performance.
In the last lecture, we motivated the need for a memory hierarchy that consisted of one
or more levels of caches between the processor pipeline and main memory.
Here, I'm showing a two-level cache hierarchy integrated in our now-familiar five-stage
pipeline processor.
Separate L1 caches are typically used for instructions and data, since in any given
clock cycle we would need to read from both simultaneously.
The upper-level caches are typically unified, storing both instructions and data.
The advantage of this organization is that while accessing main memory can be slow, if
we keep most of the instructions and data we need, often a level or two closer to the
processor, then we can minimize the number of full penalty trips to main memory.
Last time, we discussed three key design considerations for caches.
However, our discussion of placement and replacement were limited to direct mapped caches.
In this lecture, we'll cover the more general concept of set associativity.
The problem of cache placement is that the cache capacity is much smaller than main memory,
so we need a smart way of choosing where to put blocks into the cache, such that if we
tend to reuse blocks x and y often, we want to minimize the likelihood of x and y kicking
each other out of the cache.
Set associativity is the extent of flexibility that the cache has in terms of selecting where
to place the block.
Please note two new definitions.
A cache way is one possible location in the cache that a given block can be placed.
A cache set is a group of ways for a given block.
A general n-way set associative cache is one where every single block has exactly n locations
or n ways where it can be placed.
At one extreme is a direct mapped cache that we discussed before.
Here n is equal to 1, so every block has no choice but to go in its designated index.
At the other extreme is a fully associative cache where n is equal to the total number
of blocks that the cache can fit.
In this case, every block can go anywhere in the cache.
This is the standard structure of an n-way set associative cache.
As before, the cache consists of a tag array and a data array.
The difference now is that both arrays are composed of multiple sub arrays, one for each
of the n-ways.
To figure out which set of ways to use for a given block x, as before, we break it up
into bits of its memory address, into a tag, an index, in this case a set index, and a
block offset.
This is the standard hash function used to index into a cache.
The set bits select a specific index in each of the tags sub arrays.
Upon a cache lookup, all n-ways are accessed in parallel, and each of the n tags are checked
for a hit.
In parallel to this, the data array is also accessed to retrieve the n-possible data blocks.
If a tag hit is found, the corresponding block is selected and shifted based on the block
offset.
Finally, the data word for x is sent through the output port.
Consider an example cache where memory addresses are 32 bits, blocks are 64 bytes in size,
and the cache is 16-way set associative with a capacity of 128 kibabytes.
Given our standard hash function, what is the minimum number of tag bits needed?
Let's do some math.
In a 128k cache with 64 bytes per block, we know that there's storage for 2048 blocks
in this cache.
But we have 16 ways, which mean we can hold 16 cache lines per set, so we further divide
2048 by 16 and see that there are 128 sets.
Now that we have the number of sets, we can figure out the number of bits in the tag,
set, and offset.
Log 64 means 6 bits for offset, log 128 means 7 bits for set, and subtracting those from
the 32-bit address says we need 19 bits in the tag.
We could choose a different hash function than what we've chosen, but there are two
requirements.
A block cannot map to multiple locations in the cache at once, and we must never wrongly
think that block x is block y or vice versa.
Every block must be uniquely identifiable.
Okay, let's revisit cache replacement.
As discussed last time, replacement in direct map caches is straightforward because each
block only has one possible place it can go.
If an address lookup goes to an occupied entry with a different tag, it's a miss and we
have to evict.
For set associative caches, if there are n ways, then we have n possible candidates
for replacement.
In an ideal world, we would use belated optimal replacement policy where we would evict the
block that would be used furthest away in the future.
This maximizes our ability to reuse blocks in the cache effectively.
However, this policy requires perfect knowledge of the future and is impossible to achieve.
More practical common policies include FIFO, which evicts the oldest block by tracking
their ages.
The next is LRU, where we store a stack in the order of which each of the n blocks were
used.
This is a good approximation of the ladies' algorithm as it gets expensive to execute
in hardware if the associativity, aka the number of ways, is high.
A practical approximation of LRU is not most recently used.
The idea here is to track the most recently used and then evict any one of the others
randomly.
It actually turns out that this performs well in most applications.
Let's walk through an example with LRU replacement.
Here's a 32-byte cache with an associativity of two.
Some of the blocks are four bytes in size and assume a right back, right allocate policy.
Memory addresses are six bits wide.
With this organization, there are four sets in the cache, thus we need two set index bits,
two bits for the block offset, and two bits for the tag.
The right side shows the current state of the tag array, which is initially empty.
The first instruction loads address 2A.
In binary, this is 101010, thus the set index is 2.
We check the tag array and see that it's not there, so this is a cache miss.
When the block arrives, we put our tag 10 into one of the ways in set 2.
In this case, the LRU bit was pointing to way 0 initially, so that's where we'll insert
the block.
After this, way 1 becomes the least recently used in the set.
The next access is to address 2B.
This byte is within the same block as 2A, so we have a cache hit, and nothing changes
in the tag array.
The next access is 3C, which accesses set3.
This is a miss, so we fetch the block and then update the tag array with the tag and
the new LRU.
The same goes for 2-0, this time with set0.
Now the program accesses 3-3.
This block also falls into set0, but since our cache is 2-way associative, we don't
need to evict the other block currently in set0.
We have a space for two blocks at the same set index.
But now if we access the third block that falls into set0, say address 1-1, then we
are forced to kick out one of the blocks.
The one that we kick out is the least recently used, which is block 2-0, since it was accessed
furthest away in the past.
So what happens on a store?
If we store address 2-9, we access set2, and in this case we have a cache hit.
Since this is a writeback cache, we won't directly write the new value to memory yet.
Instead, we'll store the modified value in the cache and set a dirty bit to remind us
to write the value back to memory when this block eventually gets evicted.
As we saw in the previous example, low associativity may result in conflicts and evictions known
as cache thrashing.
But making associativity too high is expensive because we need more comparators to perform
the tag checks in parallel, and we expend more energy retrieving more data blocks.
One creative optimization is to build skewed associative caches.
The idea is to use different hash functions per way.
Though this requires a bit more combinational logic to implement multiple hash functions,
the benefit is that now potential collisions are more spread out in the cache.
For example, a pair of blocks x and y are less likely to constantly kick each other
out because if they have the same index in way 1, chances are they will have different
indices in way 2.
An analogy of this is to say you have a tightly packed course schedule.
With the standard scheduling scheme, it would be unfortunate but surprisingly likely that
the discussion sections of two courses that you really want to take end up conflicting
with each other every Monday, Wednesday, Friday at 1 p.m.
So you basically have to miss three discussion sections every week.
With a skewed scheduling scheme, one course may get discussion section on Monday 1 p.m.,
Wednesdays 3 p.m., and Fridays 10 a.m. while the other may get Mondays 1 p.m., Wednesdays
11 a.m. and Fridays 4 p.m.
Here the sessions still collide but only once a week on Monday.
So this way you'd be able to attend far more discussion sections and excel in those exams.
Now let's learn how to assess the performance or effectiveness of a cache.
The proxy for cache performance is its miss rate.
There are two metrics generally used to describe this miss rate.
The first is the local miss rate which is the percentage of accesses or requests to the cache
that are misses. For example, if you access the cache 50 times and five of those times is a cache
miss, then your local miss rate is 10%. As you'd expect, the local hit rate is 100% minus the
local miss rate. The second metric is the global miss rate which defines misses relative to the
program's execution. Specifically, it's the measure of the number of misses per instruction
executed. The common measure is MPKI which is the number of misses for every thousand instructions.
Conversely, you may sometimes see this as instructions per miss.
Here's a quick example of how to reason about miss rates. Say the L1 has a global miss rate of
one miss per 30 instructions and a local miss rate of 10%. Then we can infer what fraction of
the instructions in our program access the L1 either via load or store. Simply dividing the
global miss rate by the local miss rate gives us this fraction which is equal to one-third in this
case. Let's move to an example with a two-level cache hierarchy. If the global miss rate of the
L1 is one miss per 20 instructions and the global miss rate of the L2 is one miss per 80
instructions, then what is the local miss rate of the L2 cache? Remember that the L2 cache is
only ever accessed upon a miss in the L1. Since we miss in the L1 once every 20 instructions,
then we know that we access the L2 once every 20 instructions. So based on that, it's clear that one
of every four L2 accesses is a miss or 25% local miss rate.
Now that we have a sense of the miss rates, what does this mean for actual cycle performance?
A common metric for measuring the performance of the memory hierarchy is average memory access time
or AMAT. This is the number of cycles between when the processor issues a memory request
and when it's received. So with a single level cache hierarchy, average memory access time is
a function of the cache access latency here shown as TL1, its local miss rate, as well as the latency
of main memory. Basically what this is saying is that on every memory request, we incur the delay
of accessing the L1 cache, but only when it misses do we incur the delay of accessing main memory.
Note that L1 caches usually have an access latency of only one cycle.
Next, we'll extend this to a two-level hierarchy. Upon a miss in the L1, we will incur the access
latency of the L2, and only when the L2 misses will we incur the access latency of memory.
Hopefully you can see the pattern here, and this can be applied recursively for an N-level
cache hierarchy.
Let's put it all together with an example. Assume an L1 cache with a one-cycle latency
and a miss rate of 5%. Note that when we state the miss rate percentage of a cache,
generally you can assume that we're referring to its local miss rate. Assume we also have a 10-cycle
L2 cache with a 20% miss rate, and our memory has a 50-cycle delay. The question is,
if we were to remove the L2 cache, how bad would our average memory access time be?
When we have an L2, we incur the one-cycle access of the L1, 5% of the time will miss,
and thus incur the 10-cycle access of the L2, and 20% of the time will miss and incur the
50-cycle access of memory. All this means is that on average, we'll expend two cycles per load and
store. Without the L2, we need to access memory as soon as we miss in the L1, which makes our
average memory access time 3.5 cycles, which is 1.75 times higher. Adding more levels of cache can
significantly improve performance. Finally, how do we measure cache performance in conjunction
with the processor? To start, think about what happens on a cache miss. In general, we'd have
to stall our pipeline. Modern processors may actually choose to flush the pipeline instead,
since global stall logic can be pretty expensive when you have so many more functional units in
your processor. But for the purposes of our five-stage pipeline in this course, you can
generally assume that we'll stall on a cache miss. So now consider a processor with a base CPI of one
running a program with about 30% of the instructions being a loader store.
Now, if the base CPI is one, then we can assume that our L1 access latency is only one cycle.
In other words, an L1 hit can fit inside one cycle of the memory stage in our pipeline.
So then to compute the average CPI, we only need to reason about how many stall cycles we
introduce in the event of an L1 miss. But this can get a little bit tricky because we have to
remember that our processor actually has two L1 caches, one for instructions and one for data.
Say we have single-level hierarchy, where our L1 instruction cache has a miss rate of 2%,
and our L1 data cache has a miss rate of 10%. And let's assume our main memory has a delay of 10
cycles. In this case, to compute the average CPI, we first compute the penalty of a data cache miss.
In our program, we only access the data cache for 30% of the instructions,
and 10% of those are misses incurred during a 10-cycle penalty. This means our average
data cache penalty is 0.3 cycles per instruction. The instruction cache, on the other hand, is
accessed by every instruction in the fetch stage, and 2% of the time, we miss and incur the 10-cycle
memory latency. Thus, our instruction cache penalty is 0.2 cycles per instruction on average.
So adding these to our base CPI of 1, we can compute our average CPI to now be 1.5 cycles per
instruction. Let's categorize the types of cache misses. Here is what is known as the three C's
of cache misses. The first type of miss is a compulsory, or cold, miss. This is when the
program has never accessed the block since it began executing. You have no choice but to miss
in the cache for this address. The second type is a capacity miss. This is when the program
accesses more blocks than it can fit in the cache. This implies that a cache miss is inevitable,
because our cache is not big enough to fully store our program's working set. The last type
is a conflict miss. This is when we have a cache miss for a block that would have been a hit if
it weren't for the fact that placement restrictions forced another block to evict it. This happens
when we have limited associativity in the cache, which is a small number of ways. Another way to
think about it is, say block X is not the least likely to be reused, but because of limited
associativity, we need to evict it. The next time we access X, it will be a conflict miss.
To fundamentally distinguish between the types of misses, it's best to reason about their effects
in isolation. On one extreme, given an infinite-sized cache, then everything would be a hit except for
the very first access to each block. These would be cold misses. If we had a finite-sized cache,
but we made it fully associative, then every miss that isn't in the first access,
as in every miss that isn't a cold miss, is a capacity miss. In other words, conflict misses
won't exist because there are no placement restrictions in a fully associative cache.
Conflict misses can only occur when a block only has a subset of the cache to be placed.
To see their effects, let's look at how types of misses vary depending on the
cache capacity and associativity. The first artifact to note is that compulsory misses
are an artifact of the program, so they're the same regardless of the cache's capacity
and associativity. The second thing to notice is that increasing the associativity while keeping
the capacity fixed results in a decrease in conflict misses, but doesn't affect the capacity
misses. This makes sense since the cache size is unchanged and all we've done is reduce the
amount of placement restrictions. Now let's try varying the capacity and block size.
This time, if we fix the capacity but increase the block size,
we find that the number of cold misses go down. Why? Well, by increasing the block size,
we are fetching more data into the cache per miss, which increases the likelihood
of hitting spatial locality. What's interesting is that with larger blocks,
the number of capacity and conflict misses can actually increase. This may not seem intuitive
at first, but the reason is that increasing the block size actually means fewer blocks in the cache.
So if our program doesn't have perfect spatial locality and isn't fully utilizing all of the
data in each block, then we are actually hurting ourselves and potentially causing more misses.
I encourage you to reason about how this chart would look if our program instead had perfect
spatial locality.
So now that we know about the different types of misses, we can reason about potential
optimizations in our cache design. If we want to reduce capacity misses, obviously increasing
the cache size is the way to go. But if that's not feasible, you can modify the program to improve
its temporal locality. In other words, if we are getting cache misses because our working
set is too big, and some of our data is getting kicked out before we reuse it, then ideally,
we'd want to target spatial locality and fully use each piece of data when we bring it into the
cache so that when it does get evicted, we won't ever need to use it again.
In terms of conflict misses, increasing the associativity helps as well as improving the
replacement policy of the hash function, as we saw in the skewed associative cache.
And finally, reducing cold misses is a little tougher. As was discussed, increasing the block
size and or the program's spatial locality helps. Another option is to implement a common technique
called prefetching, which uses prediction to fetch a block into the cache before we actually access
it. This is an active research area and has a lot of cool work.
Let's wrap up this lecture with a couple of exercises. Consider the C program running on a
processor with a 4K fully associative data cache with 64 byte blocks and LRU replacement.
How many cold misses will we get? Try to take some time to work through it.
Let's visualize the hits and misses. With 64 byte blocks, each block can hold 16
4 byte integers from array A. Since we're looking at cold misses, then we're only concerned with
the first iteration of the N loop, which is when N is equal to 0. Because subsequent iterations
will just access the array again. So in the beginning of the loop, we access A sub 0,
which is a cold miss, but this also fetches the next 15 integers. And because we're accessing
the array sequentially, all 15 of these will be cache hits. Then when we access A sub 16,
we have another cold miss followed by 15 cache hits. This pattern continues and we find that
one sixteenth of our accesses in the first iteration of the N loop is a cold miss,
leading to 2048 cold misses in total.
Now how many capacity misses are there? Please pause and try to work through this one also.
As we just showed, all of the misses in the first iteration of the N loop are cold misses.
So we must only focus on the next two iterations of integer N.
When N is equal to one, we see the same pattern of one miss per 15 hits. But this time,
this is a capacity miss. That's because the array A is 128k in size, which is larger than the 4k
cache. And we know that these aren't conflict misses because our cache is fully associative.
So then like before, we end up with 2048 misses when N is equal to one, except this time these are
all capacity misses. When N is equal to two, we see the same pattern and get 2048 more misses.
Thus in total, we have 4096 capacity misses.
So in total for this program, we end up with 6144 cache misses.
Now what would happen if we were to interchange the two loops? That is,
we move the N loop to the inside. How many misses would we have now?
Please pause and take a moment to work through this one.
Visualizing the accesses, we see that when we get the first integers a sub zero,
we get a cold miss, but then we access a sub zero two more times, resulting in two hits.
At the same time, we fetch 15 more integers along with a zero, each of which are access
three times, leading to 45 more hits. So we end up with this pattern where we have one cold miss
for every 47 hits. In total, this yields only 2048 misses for the program.
So why did this reduce our cache misses so much? It's because we improved temporal locality with
our program. By interchanging the loops, we made sure to access each piece of data as much
as possible right away as soon as we brought it into the cache. So instead of fetching a zero,
using it once, then going through the entire array before fetching a zero again,
we are now simply using a zero as much as possible, the first and only time that we
fetch it. So by improving temporal locality, we actually managed to eliminate all of the
capacity misses in our program as nothing gets evicted that needs to be accessed in the future.